我们刚刚找到了一种描述变化率之间关系的方法
We have just worked out a way to describe the relationship between the rate of change
它的关节角度以及机器人末端执行器的平移和角速度。
of its joint angles and the translational and angular velocity of the robot’s end-effector.
空间速度是六向量，包括平移速度v和角度
Spatial velocity is a six-vector that comprises the translational velocity, v, and the angular
速度，欧米茄。并且，我们写了末端效应器的空间速度之间的关系
velocity, omega. And, we wrote a relationship between spatial velocity of the end-effector
和关节角度的速度。
and the velocity of the joint angles.
对于像这样的机器人，雅可比矩阵J是6×6矩阵。这是方形的。所以，我们
For a robot like this, the Jacobian matrix, J, is a 6 x 6 matrix. It’s square. So, we
可以重新排列这个表达式，以获得我们需要的机器人关节角速度
can rearrange this expression to obtain the robot joint angle velocity that we need in
为了达到理想的机器人末端效应器空间速度，我们可以做到这一点，除非
order to achieve a desired robot end-effector spatial velocity and we can do this unless
雅可比是奇异的。这是它的决定因素等于零。
the Jacobian is singular. That is its determinant is equal to zero.
不幸的是，在某些情况下，雅可比人将是单数和一个
Unfortunately, there are some circumstances where the Jacobian will be singular and one
如图所示，当关节角度θ等于零时，出现奇点。要是我们
of the singularities occurs when joint angle five is equal to zero as shown here. If we
旋转关节4，我们可以看到机器人末端执行器是如何移动的。如果我移动关节6，我们就看到了
rotate joint 4, we can see how the robot end-effector moves. If I move joint 6, we see that the
末端执行器的运动完全相同;这是由于关节4.所以，如果我旋转关节
end-effector motion is exactly the same; it’s that due to joint 4. So, if I rotate joints
如图4和6所示，它们在相反的方向上相互抵消。他们都在动，但是
4 and 6 in opposite directions, they cancel each other out. They are both moving, but
末端执行器根本不动。
the end-effector is not moving at all.
继前面的例子之后，我们可以测试雅可比矩阵的行列式
Following on from the earlier example, we can test the determinant of the Jacobian matrix
用于关节角度配置QN。而且，在这里我们可以看到行列式，它就是
for the joint angle configuration QN. And, here we can see the determinant, and it’s
不等于零。这意味着我可以反转雅可比矩阵，这就是逆
not equal to zero. It means I can then invert the Jacobian matrix and this is what the inverse
雅可比人看起来像。如果我们考虑不同的关节角度配置，我会去
Jacobian looks like. If we consider a different joint angle configuration, I’m going to
查看关节配置Q0，即所有关节角度等于零的位置。
look at the joint configuration Q0 which is where all the joint angles equal to zero.
如果我在这里计算雅可比行列并通过QZ，我们可以看到这就是雅可比人的样子
If I compute the Jacobian here and pass in QZ, we can see this is what the Jacobian looks
喜欢和这个特定情况下的决定因素等于零。
like and the determinant in this particular case is equal to zero.
所以，让我们说，我有一个机器人控制问题，我希望机器人末端执行器有
So, let’s say, I’ve got a robot control problem and I want the robot end-effector to have
由希腊字母nu表示的非常特定的空间速度，那么我可以找出什么
a very specific spatial velocity denoted by the Greek letter nu, then I can work out what
我需要的联合速度才能实现这一目标。如果我知道关节角度，那么
joint velocity I need in order to achieve that. If I know the joint angles, and then
我可以计算雅可比矩阵并将其反转。然后，我移动所有关节
I can compute the Jacobian matrix and invert it. And then, I move all the joints at that
特定的速度和机器人末端执行器将以所需的空间速度移动，
particular speed and the robot end-effector will move with the desired spatial velocity,
NU。现在，问题在于，因为机器人关节角度在短时间内发生变化，
nu. Now, the problem is that because the robot joint angles are changing, after a short while,
雅各比派将不再合适，因为雅可比行列式是雅各比派的一个功能
the Jacobian will be no longer appropriate because the Jacobian is a function of the
关节角度。所以，我需要重新计算雅可比矩阵。
joint angles. So, I will need to recompute the Jacobian matrix.
如果我要写一个计算机算法来做这件事，那将是一种离散时间
If I was to write a computer algorithm to do this, it would be a type of discrete time
算法。它将在许多离散时间步骤，时间步骤1，时间计算
algorithm. It would be computed at a number of discrete time steps, time step 1, time
步骤2，时间步骤3，我将其推广到时间步骤k。而且，之间的间隔
step 2, time step 3, and I’ll generalize that to time step k. And, the interval between
时间步长由符号deltaT给出。因此，在时间步长k，我将采用关节角度
time steps is given by the symbol delta T. So, at time step, k, I will take the joint angles
这是在时间测量的，k。我计算雅可比矩阵，将其反转，乘以期望值
that’s measured at time, k. I compute the Jacobian, invert it, multiply it by the desired
空间速度并确定我需要达到的关节角速度。如果我成倍增加
spatial velocity and determine the joint angle velocity that I need to achieve. If I multiply
通过时间间隔ΔT的关节速度，然后我获得关节角度的变化
the joint velocity by the time interval, delta T, then I obtain the change in joint angles
在那个时间步骤。我把它添加到当前的关节角度组中，我最终得到了
over that time step. I add it to the current set of joint angles and I end up with the
我需要在下一个时间步，在时间k+1处拥有的一组关节角度。然后
set of joint angles that I need to have at the next time step, at time k+1. And, then
我告诉我的机器人移动到那组新的关节角度，我重复这个过程。
I tell my robot to move to that new set of joint angles and I repeat the process.
我们现在将研究解决率运动控制。而且，我已经计算了
We are now going to look at resolved-rate motion control. And, I have already computed the
关于角度集的雅可比矩阵，我称之为QN。现在，我想做的是
Jacobian matrix for the set of joint angles which I call QN. Now, what I want to do is
指定我希望机器人拥有的空间速度。我要说的
to specify the spatial velocity that I want my robot to have. I’m going to put that
在一个名为nu的变量中，这是我用来表示空间速度的希腊字母
in to a variable called, nu, which is the Greek letter that I used to denote spatial velocity
我要求x的空间速度为零，y为零，每个单位为1
and I am going to ask for a spatial velocity of zero in x, zero in the y, one unit per
z方向上的第二个并且没有角速度。而且，我将把它放到专栏中
second in the z direction and no angular velocity. And, I’m going to put that in to a column
向量。因此，我们有它。如果我现在将雅可比行列的倒数乘以所需的
vector. So, there we have it. If I now multiply the inverse of the Jacobian by the desired
空间速度，这里我所知的是关节角速度矢量。这是
spatial velocity, and what I have here is the joint angle velocity vector. This is the
一组关节角速度，它将给我所需的空间速度矢量
set of joint angle velocities that will give me the desired spatial velocity vector that’s
在垂直方向或z方向上每秒一个单位的运动。
a motion of one unit per second in the vertical or z direction.
我们可以看到它对于关节1和4完全不涉及运动，并且它确实需要运动
We can see that it involves no motion at all for joints 1 and 4 and it does require motion
关节2和3。这是肩关节和肘关节，也是关节5，其中之一
of joints 2 and 3. That’s the shoulder and the elbow joint and also joint 5, one of the
腕关节。并且，我们可以看到所有关节，它是肘关节，关节3
wrist joints. And, we can see that of all the joints, it is the elbow joint, joint 3
必须移动最快才能达到所需的运动。
that has to move the fastest in order to achieve the desired motion.
这是一个动画，在实践中显示了这一点。我命令机器人垂直移动
Here is an animation that shows this in practice. I have commanded the robot to move vertically
在世界z方向上具有正1的速度。我们观察到机器人末端执行器
with a velocity of positive 1 in the world z direction. We observed that the robot end-effector
以恒定速度移动。但是，如果我们看一下关节角度如何随函数变化
moved that in constant velocity. But, if we look at how the joint angles change as a function
时间，我们看到他们没有线性移动。
of time, we see that they are not moving linearly.
我们也知道一些关节角度的速度正在增加。而且，你注意到了
We also know that some of the joint angles are increasing in velocity. And, you notice
当机器人到达那个动作结束时，它看起来有点尴尬。它
that as the robot got to the end of that motion, it started to look a little bit awkward. It
只能在z方向上移动这么久。最终，它无法做到
can only move in the z direction for so long. Eventually, it’s not going to be able to
达到它需要移动的位置。
reach the position that it needs to move to.